[Music]
oh bosum is now the UK's most Innovative
seafront and home to Europe's first
artificial surf Reef thanks to an 11
million pound regeneration scheme The
Reef is the first of its kind in the
northern hemisphere its effect on the
seafront and Community are clear to see
and the area has been transformed bosam
is a short walk away from Bournemouth
the UK's leading seaside resort in his
Victorian Heyday bosam was the place to
be people traveled from all over the
country to Holiday there as it was
believed it Spa water and pine trees
were health-giving however in recent
decades lack of investment saw the area
decline in
1999 the idea of creating an artificial
surf Reef was first raised the freeto
use Sports facility would attract
visitors and encourage regeneration in
the area Bournemouth burough Council
sold an underused car park to finance
the scheme but it wasn't until 2007 that
the council received special permission
from the government to build the
reef The Reef is made from a base layer
a top layer and a ramp which Points
seawoods each layer consists of two
elements a webbing base and huge
geotextile bags geotextile means that
the special material is environmentally
friendly and actually attracts marine
life which grows on the bags the webbing
base and empty sandbags arrived in
Bournemouth in summer 2008 the base was
laid out onto a field and the first
section of sandbags was attached to it
the section was then concertina by huge
cranes and laid onto a barge ready for
transportation to the Marine
construction site in August 2008
Bournemouth finally had the perfect
weather conditions required to lay the
first section onto bosam seabed just
east of bosam Pier watched by National
TV Crews and journalists from all over
the country divers went down and
carefully attached one end of the first
Reef section to Anchor blocks a barge
was then slowly pulled out and the
section sank onto the seabed then the
construction team pumped each bag full
of sand that had been specially
harvested on boson Beach the largest
bags were 70 M long 2 m high and 6 M
wide the base layer of the reef was
completed but poor weather meant that
work had to stop until spring
2009 eventually in the Autumn the top
layer and ramp was laid and filled to
complete Europe's first artificial surf
Reef it's the size of a football pitch
and positioned 250 M offshore to make
waves break further away from the beach
and provide a longer ride it does not
work like a wave machine would as it
does not create waves where none exist
if the sea is calm and flat it will
remain so however if there's a good siiz
swell it mimics a natural Reef by acting
as a ramp pushing existing waves upwards
and channels them along the length of
the structure the natural waves are
enhanced and they break with more power
than those on the beach creating
right-hander waves for Surfers and body
Borders The Reef is an additional surf
break to those either side of bosam and
Bournemouth Pier it's free to Surf and
the the rnli provides safety cover on
the reef 365 days of the year The Reef
has also had a positive effect on marine
life as a variety of species now live on
the reef including crabs Lobster pipe
fish seab bass and mullet as a result of
this unique project bosam has enjoyed
Global publicity gaining coverage in
over 60 countries worldwide new hotels
shops and restaurants have opened up and
given bosam a boost around 80 jobs have
been created along the seafront alone
The Reef has been a catalyst for change
as the seafront has been transformed and
now hosts changing facilities and warm
showers bosin Pier end has been rebuilt
and is a great platform to watch Surfers
and body boarders in action the seafront
also hosts the famous Beach pods which
are Beach huts with a modern twist they
have been interior designed by fashion
designers Wayne and Jardine Hemingway
and each one offers a retro interior
kitchenet bespoke Beach furniture and
fantastic sea views from a private
balcony the beach pods are available to
buy and rent from the seafront
office visitors can now come down to
bosam stay in a boutique hotel eat in a
glamorous seafront restaurant bask in
the renovated Gardens learn to surf
kayak or bodyboard and enjoy a brand new
bosum the UK's most Innovative
seafront for more information please
visit bornemouth deco.